Campus Unrest Collection; Collection ua950.007
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Campus Unrest Collection
1967-1972
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ua950.007
1.53 cubic ft.
The Campus Unrest Collection documents volatile events during the late 1960s and the early 1970s that occurred not only at the State University Of New York at Albany, but at other Universities as well.
Biographical Sketch
The Campus Unrest Collection focuses on volatile events involving students that occurred at the State University of New York at Albany (now the University at Albany), as well as other campuses around the country. Inspired by national and local influences, these events occurred in the late 1960s and early 1970s and involved student-faculty relations, race relations, the Vietnam War, and the shootings at Kent State University. All served to raise tension among students, faculty and administration, most noticeably during the 1969-1970 academic year.
At colleges and universities around the country, this period witnessed the end of the institution serving "in loco parentis" or in place of parents. Universities, including the State University of New York at Albany, allowed for greater freedom of the student body by removing curfews and dress codes. Students transitioned away from older campus traditions and established new ones. Many students (and faculty) protested the escalation of U.S. troops serving in Vietnam.
While these national trends were in evidence at the State University of New York at Albany, other institution-specific developments also affected campus life. The school became a State University of New York (SUNY) University Center in 1962, opened its expanded Uptown Campus for classes in the Fall of 1966 and the size of the student body grew exponentially and became more diverse. As a result, administrators and faculty no longer shared personal connections with as many students, severely affecting two-way communication. The University also responded to the heterogeneity of the student population. Then President Evan R. Collins created the Afro-American Studies department in January 1969 in direct response to demands by an increasing African-American student population, led by the Black Student Alliance, for entry level courses in Afro-American studies. The new department offered its first courses in Fall 1969. The following year, the Department of Judaic Studies opened.
On October 15, 1969, the State University of New York at Albany participated in events for a national Vietnam Moratorium day. The University held a twenty-four hour vigil during which the names of those killed in the Vietnam War were read on the academic podium. Speeches and workshops also were held.
During March 1970, the State University of New York at Albany did not renew the two-year contract of popular assistant professor Gerard Wagner of the Department of Rhetoric and Public Address. As part of reaction to this news, students protested, some broke windows and others occupied the halls outside of Acting President Allan A. Kuusito's office.
In the early spring of 1970, African-American faculty and students submitted several proposals addressing racism on campus to the administration. Proposals included seeking better representation of black students among Resident Assistants, hiring of black food service workers, and issuance of guidelines to existing staff and faculty about treating all students equally. These groups also documented reports of racial incidents on campus. This communication was one part of an ongoing discussion of race relations on the campus. In April 1970 African-American students became angered at the policy of checking student identification in order to eat in the cafeteria resulting in two incidents in the Colonial Quad dining room. According to students, this policy of strict identification checking was not the norm in Colonial Quad and some believed that African-American students were unfairly singled out. In the more volatile, second incident, approximately 75 students allegedly assaulted a cafeteria supervisor, broke windows, threw food and upturned tables.
Students overall also demanded greater participation in University decision making, especially following the anger over the contract renewal debate about Gerard Wagner. In response, the University suspended classes and held two Dialogue Days in March of 1970 where students attended workshops such as "Legal Procedures - Amnesty for Students," "Racism on Campus," and "50-50 Faculty-Student Control of the University." Departments held meetings with students and the Library invited students to come by at any time to meet, convene or suggest ideas. As part of the dialogue with faculty and administration, students aired grievances about many aspects of University life from the University Senate (more student representation necessary) to the Library (request for one central circulation desk) to advising services (inadequate).
Other sources of tension on campus during 1969-1970 prompted additional student activism. These included a women's group's ultimately unsuccessful attempt to establish an on-campus child care facility, conflict with the academic calendar and religious holidays, drug arrests by police and a People's Park demonstration which delayed construction of two courtyards on the academic podium.
The events of this volatile school year culminated in May 1970 when the Nixon Administration announced U.S. troop movement into Cambodia, touching off unrest at campuses across the country, helping lead to the shootings at Kent State on May 4. State University of New York at Albany students protested and demonstrated their anger by vandalizing the Library on the night of May 4. On May 6, 1500-2000 students gathered en masse and marched to downtown Albany where the group burned an effigy of President Richard Nixon and listened to speeches. Other disruptions of regular campus activities in the days following Kent State included bomb scares, the throwing of fire bombs and Molotov cocktails, destruction of campus property in addition to the Library, fires in residence halls and repeated false fire alarms. The University also canceled several events including Alumni Day, Parents Weekend and a University Community Symphony Orchestra. Many students did not attend classes at the end of the semester. Some elected to strike because of the myriad of immediate events, the many fire alarms disrupted classes and some students cited fear for their personal safety as a reason for leaving campus before the semester officially ended. As a result, President Kuusito issued special guidelines and alternatives to faculty on May 12, 1970 regarding the completion of course work during a crisis.
Compared to other colleges and universities in the SUNY system, the State University of New York at Albany experienced less vandalism and damage on campus than other schools during 1969-1970. According to a report prepared by John J. Mather, assistant to SUNY Chancellor Samuel B. Gould, and issued in July 1970, the total amount of damages at 26 SUNY schools for 1969-1970 was $518,000. Albany's share was only $85,000 compared to $233,000 at SUNY Buffalo. The bulk of damage occurred on and immediately after May 4, 1970.
Scope and Contents
This is an artificial collection, including correspondence, newspaper clippings, and fliers and printed materials, predominantly from 19691970, collected to document unrest on the State University of New York at Albany campus and at other institutions across the country. The majority of the material from the University at Albany details events from the Spring Semester 1970. Alice Hastings, the University Librarian, Fredericks Volkwein, Assistant Dean of Graduate Studies, and Dr. Frederick D. Weinstein of the School of Library Science gathered the collection as background information for a 1971 report on campus unrest at the request of the Acting Vice President for Academic Affairs. The report is found in Series 1.
Of interest to researchers may be shards of glass resulting from the vandalism and unrest on the University at Albany campus following the Kent State shootings on May 4, 1970.
For researchers interested in more materials on campus unrest, please see the following related collections: John J. Mather Papers (APAP-107) Series 2, Subseries 1 and the Vietnam War Collection (UA-950.006). Please see the Department of Africana Studies Records for materials related to the introduction of Afro-American Studies at the university.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Unrest at the University at Albany, 1968-1972, Undated
Series 2 - Unrest at Universities Across the Country, 1967-1971
All series are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Acquisition Information
The collection was gathered as background information for a 1971 report on campus unrest at the request of the Acting Vice President for Academic Affairs by the University Librarian, Alice Hastings, Fredericks Volkwein, Assistant Dean of Graduate Studies, and Dr. Frederick D. Weinstein of the School of Library Science.
Related Materials
Related collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives can be found in the subject guide for Criminal Justice and Prisons.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Military and Armed Conflict; Campus violence--New York (State)--Albany.; Student movements--New York (State)--Albany; College students--Political activity--New York (State)--Albany.; Albany (N.Y.); Clippings; Correspondence; Files by subject; Fliers (printed matter); UAlbany Reference Collections; State University of New York at Albany; Columbia University; Syracuse University; State University of New York at Buffalo; University of Illinois at Urbana-Champagne; University of Wisconsin-Madison
- Unrest at the University at Albany, 1968-1972; 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains reports, newspapers and clippings, correspondence, flyers, meeting minutes and notes documenting tension and unrest at the State University of New York at Albany. The bulk of material is from the 1969-1970 academic year and was created by University students, faculty, staff and administrators.
  - Academic Credit for Cancelled Classes, 1970 May-1970 June (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 1)
  - Administrative Evaluation of Crisis, 1970 June (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 2)
  - Black Panthers, ca. 1970 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 3)
  - Campus Disorder Study by Professor Brown, 1969-1970 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 4)
  - Campus Unrest Report by J. Fredericks Volkwein, 1970 December 10; 1971 January 05 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 5)
  - Communications/Community Relations, 1970 March-1970 April (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 6)
  - Communications/Community Relations, 1970 May-1970 June; 1971; Undated (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 7)
  - Curriculum and Grading, 1970; Undated (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 8)
  - Day Care Center-Women's Liberation Front, 1970 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 9)
  - Dialogue Days-Departmental Meetings, 1970 March 19-1970 March 20 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 10)
  - Dialogue Days-Memorandum, 1970 March 19-1970 March 20 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 11)
  - Dialogue Days-Plenary Session, 1970 May 21 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 12)
  - Dialogue Days-Recommendations, 1970 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 13)
  - Dialogue Days-Suggestions, 1970 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 14)
  - Dialogue Days-Workshops, 1970 March 19-1970 March 20 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 15)
  - Faculty Activities, 1968-1970 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 16)
  - Faculty Meetings and Resolutions, 1970 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 17-18)
  - Faculty Writings and Campus Unrest, 1969-1970 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 19)
  - FBI Airmail Correspondence, 1967-1976 (Box 2 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 20)
  - FBI Investigation and Correspondence, 1939-1941 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 21)
  - FBI Investigation and Correspondence, 1942-1947 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 22)
  - FBI Investigation and Correspondence, 1948-1957 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 23)
  - FBI Investigation and Correspondence, 1964-1968 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 24)
  - FBI Investigation and Correspondence, 1969-1979 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 25)
  - Federal Government Correspondence and Reports, 1970; Undated (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 26)
  - Legislative Correspondence and Reports, 1970 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 27)
  - Liberation Classes (Strike School), 1970 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 28)
  - Library Vandalism, 1970 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 29)
  - Logs of Campus Unrest (Schedules), 1970 Spring (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 30)
  - Newspapers -Albany Student Press, 1970 March-1970 October (Oversized 1, Folder 31)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1969-1971 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 32)
  - Newspapers - Panther 21/New York 21 Trial News, 1970 October-1971 February (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 33)
  - Newspapers - Protests/Small Press Newspapers, 1969-1970; Undated (Oversized 1, Folder 34)
  - Newspapers -Tower Tribune, 1970 April-1970 July (Oversized 1, Folder 35)
  - Peoples Park (Protest of Construction on Campus), 1970 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 36)
  - Presidential and Administrative Memos to the Campus Community, 1970 March-1970 June (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 37)
  - Racial Incidents, 1969-1970 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 38)
  - Referendum, 1969-1970 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 39)
  - Rules for the Maintenance of Public Order (SUNY Regulations), 1969-1970 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 40)
  - Security, 1969-1970 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 41)
  - State Education Department Memorandum and Statements, 1970 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 42)
  - Student and Protest Writings, 1969-1972; Undated (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 43)
  - Student Disciplinary Proceedings, 1968-1970 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 44)
  - Student Flyers and Notices, 1969-1971 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 45)
  - Student Flyers and Notices, Undated (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 46)
  - Student Housing, 1970 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 47)
  - Student Petitions, 1969-1970; Undated (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 48)
  - Temporary State Commission to Study Causes of Campus Unrest, 1969-1970 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 49)
  - Tenure Disputes, 1969-1970; Undated (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 50)
  - Vietnam Moratorium Day, 1969 October 15 (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 51)
  - Vietnam War - Writings and Pamphlets, Undated (Box 1 (1-Unrest at the University at Albany), Folder 52)
- Unrest at Universities Across the Country, 1967-1971; 2
  In the summer of 1970, Alice Hasting sent inquiries to other universities asking for background materials documenting the "student unrest movement" on their respecitve campuses. This series contains the results she received including general information about unrest at colleges and universities across the United States. There also are folders devoted to the University at Buffalo, Columbia University, Yale University, the University of Chicago, the University of Michigan and the University of Wisconsin. The series contains correspondence, reports, newspapers and clippings.
  - Columbia University, 1968 (Box 2 (2-Unrest at Universities Across the Country), Folder 1)
  - Correspondence Requesting Materials, 1970 (Box 2 (2-Unrest at Universities Across the Country), Folder 2)
  - Illinois Alumni News, 1970 (Oversized 1, Folder 4)
  - National Association of State University and Land Grant Colleges (NASULGC), 1969-1970 (Box 2 (2-Unrest at Universities Across the Country), Folder 3)
  - Pamphlet: Control of Student Disorders by Raymond Momboisse, 1968 (Box 2 (2-Unrest at Universities Across the Country), Folder 4)
  - Publications, 1968 (Box 2 (2-Unrest at Universities Across the Country), Folder 5)
  - Stanford University, 1970 (Box 2 (2-Unrest at Universities Across the Country), Folder 6)
  - State University of New York News, 1970 (Oversized 1, Folder 5)
  - Syracuse University, 1970 (Box 2 (2-Unrest at Universities Across the Country), Folder 7)
  - University at Buffalo, 1970 (Box 2 (2-Unrest at Universities Across the Country), Folder 8-9)
  - University of Chicago, 1970 (Box 3 (2-Unrest at Universities Across the Country), Folder 1)
  - University of Illinois, 1969-1970 (Box 3 (2-Unrest at Universities Across the Country), Folder 2)
  - University of Michigan, 1970 (Box 3 (2-Unrest at Universities Across the Country), Folder 3)
  - University of Wisconsin at Madison, 1970-1971 (Box 3 (2-Unrest at Universities Across the Country), Folder 4)
  - Writings (General), 1967-1970 (Box 3 (2-Unrest at Universities Across the Country), Folder 5)
  - Yale University, 1970 (Box 3 (2-Unrest at Universities Across the Country), Folder 6)